Guide to the Joni Rabinowitz Papers, 1957-2008 AIS.2010.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Joni Rabinowitz Papers
1957-2008
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rabinowitz, Joni
AIS.2010.05
12.21 Linear Feet (11 boxes; 1 oversize box)
This collection contains the papers of Joni Rabinowitz, a Pittsburgh socialist and activist who has been involved in a number of organizations issues, and movements relating to social, political, and economic justice since the 1960s, such as the New American Movement. Included are organizational records, leftist counterculture literature, legal records, personal papers, and materials relating to the many issues, projects and campaigns, in which Rabinowitz has been involved.
Biography
Joni Rabinowitz was born on July 30, 1941 in Brooklyn, New York. She grew up in New Rochelle, a suburb of New York City. Her father, Victor, a lawyer, represented trade unions and others whose unpopular ideas made finding legal representation difficult. Although her mother, Marcia, had advanced education, she remained a home maker and became a community activist who worked to integrate the public schools in New Rochelle.
In 1959 Rabinowitz graduated from New Rochelle High School and entered Antioch College, a liberal arts college located in Yellow Springs, Ohio, that offered "cooperative education programs where students alternate between on-campus study and off-campus work." Having grown up playing the cello, she entered as a Music major, but by her senior year, she changed her major to Political Science. She was active in various left political causes during her college years, including a period in 1963 when she went to Albany, Georgia, to volunteer for voter registration work with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). This was part of her co-op experience at Antioch. While in Georgia, she was arrested three times on the street for vagrancy (charges later dropped), and fasted in jail once for fifteen days and once for nine days. She was also charged with perjury by a federal grand jury and tried along with eight others as the "Albany Nine." Although she was convicted, the 5th Circuit Court eventually reversed the conviction.
In addition to civil rights, Rabinowitz while at Antioch was also active in Fair Play for Cuba (she helped organize a student trip to Cuba at Christmas time 1960), attended the Helsinki Youth Conference in 1961, and worked for peace, free speech and socialism. In 1964, along with over 100 other protestors, Rabinowitz was arrested for demonstrating against a Yellow Springs barber who would not serve African-American patrons. She completed her Bachelor of Arts degree at Antioch in 1965.
Rabinowitz completed one year of Social Work school at Adelphi University in New York. During this time, together with students from other social work schools in New York, she worked to support civil rights work in the South. In the summer of 1966, she worked with the California Migrant Ministry in the San Joaquin Valley as a community organizer among Mexican-American farm workers. After this experience, she returned to New York to take a job with the New York City Welfare Department, where she remained until 1969. She was also involved with the local Social Service Employees Union (SSEU), welfare rights, and opposition to the U.S. involvement in Vietnam. Her SSEU involvement lead to her being arrested three times during a strike in 1968. The SSEU was independent, but eventually merged with District Council 31 of AFSCME (American Federation of State, County and Municipal Workers). Rabinowitz was also part of Movement for a Democratic Society (MDS), a local New York "grown up SDS" which had chapters in the welfare department, teachers, city planners and cab drivers.
While providing draft counseling for the union in New York, she met John Haer, who later became her husband. In 1969 they moved to Pittsburgh where his draft board had sent him to do alternative service at Mayview State Hospital, as a conscientious objector during the Vietnam War.
In the early 1970s Rabinowitz helped organize a 24 hour telephone hotline for youth, known as the "Switchboard," and wrote for and distributed an underground newspaper, the Pittsburgh Fair Witness. Also during this period she worked with the Gulf Action Project and other groups around the country in anti-corporate campaigns. In 1974 Rabinowitz earned a Masters of Social Work degree in community organizing from the University of Pittsburgh.
In 1971 she was a founding member of the New American Movement (NAM). This nationwide socialist-feminist organization promoted democratic socialism, feminism, economic democracy, anti-racism, labor unions, gay rights, anti-war actions, international solidarity, women's rights, civil rights, and utility reform. It aimed to create a broad movement for American socialism. It also had an extensive education program, both internal and also for the public. Additionally, NAM sponsored cultural events, such as films and folk-singers and groups. In 1973 the Pittsburgh chapter produced a slide show, "Pittsburgh 1902, a People's History" and also created a People's History of Pittsburgh wall calendar for 1973. In 1982 NAM merged with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) to form the Democratic Socialists of America (DSA). Rabinowitz was one of the minority of members, nationally, who opposed the merger.
Rabinowitz was a leader in both the local and Industrial Heartland Region organizations of NAM. Between 1971 and 1982, she was off-and-on again a Steering Committee member in the Pittsburgh Chapter, and also attended every annual national convention during those ten years. Along with her husband and several others in the Pittsburgh chapter, she was on the committee which published the NAM Newsletter, a monthly publication beginning in 1972, which was mailed to several hundred interested people. In 1982, after the merger, the name changed to the Allegheny Socialist and was published for several years after that. She was also involved in the Peoples Power Project, a NAM campaign for utility reform, from 1976-1980. In 1974-1975 she worked through NAM on a City Budget Campaign, organized to get Pittsburgh City council to fund more human services.
Between 1979 and 1982, Rabinowitz managed Wobblie Joe's, a small bar on the South Side of Pittsburgh owned by some friends who hoped to bring together the mill-worker culture with the music of Appalachia. The bar had live music every night -- at least two nationally-known figures got their start there: folk singer Anne Feeney and blues singer Ernie Hawkins. Economic problems were the primary cause of the bar's closing in 1982. Rabinowitz and the co-owners also had disagreements with the staff, which were solved by the staff forming a union.
In 1983 Rabinowitz took a job as a public policy advocate for the Hunger Action Coalition. Two years later the organization split and Rabinowitz helped found Just Harvest, an anti-hunger and anti-poverty advocacy organization. She remained as one of two co-directors at Just Harvest until 2010, when she retired. During her 25 years at Just Harvest, she organized on the national, state and local level for public policies which benefit poor and hungry people. These included food stamp policy, school meals, and welfare policies, among others.
Currently, Rabinowitz lives in Pittsburgh with her husband and two cats, Claudette and Tippy. Since her retirement, her activities include volunteering at a cat shelter, being elected to her neighborhood board, gardening, and organizing against Marcellus Shale drilling.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into six series, five of which have been further arranged into subseries. Folders within subseries are organized alphabetically, excluding the series devoted to campaigns and legal cases, which are organized chronologically. Additional scope and content notes are found at the series and subseries level.
Series I. New American Movement (NAM)
Series II. Democratic Socialists of America (DSA)
Series III. Campaign Involvement
Series IV. Topics and Organizations
Series V. Literature
Series VI. Personal
Scope and Content Notes
The Joni Rabinowitz Papers, which date from 1957 to 2008, document her personal life and constant involvement and devotion to social, political and economic justice issues. Her papers trace her activism in college and the historic civil rights cases she was involved in, her activism in New York City, and her move to Pittsburgh where she helped found the local chapter of the New American Movement (NAM). A majority of the collection documents her involvement in a number of leftist/socialist organizations like the NAM, Democratic Socialists of America (DSA), Voter REP, and the Rainbow Political Action Committee. Devoted to bringing awareness to social and economic inequality, she was involved in a number of movements and organizations regarding race, class, hunger, and welfare rights. Her papers also demonstrate her political concerns and intellectual interests through literature she collected concerning issues and organizations that existed throughout the 1960s and 1970s.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Related Material
Rabinowitz Social Service Unionism Collection, 1957-1969, AIS.1980.19, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
New American Movement, Pittsburgh Chapter Records, 1973-1982, AIS.1989.18, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Paul J. LeBlanc Papers, 1968-1998, AIS.1974.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Robert Opie Shepherd Papers Relating to the Democratic Socialists of America, AIS.1990.21, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Political and Social Activist Movements Collection, 1968-1975, AIS.1974.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
James Dolsen Political Left Pamphlets Collection, 1918-1996, AIS.1999.11, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Lawrence F. Evans Collection, 1978-1988, AIS.1988.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joni Rabinowitz in 2010 and 2011.
Political activists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Political activists -- United States; Activists; Associations; Correspondence; Personal papers; Politics; Labor movement -- United States; Social action; Labor movement -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Women; Welfare rights movement -- United States; Welfare rights movement -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Civil rights -- United States; Civil rights -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Feminism -- United States; Feminism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Radicalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Radicalism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social movements -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Rabinowitz, Victor; Antioch College; New American Movement (Organization); New American Movement (Organization). Pittsburgh Chapter; Democratic Socialists of America; Democratic Socialists of America. Pittsburgh Chapter; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); National Rainbow Coalition (U.S.); Jackson, Jesse; Movement for a Democratic Society; Social Service Employees Union; Just Harvest (Organization); Rabinowitz, Joni
- New American Movement (NAM), 1971-1985; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series documents the regional chapter of the New American Movement (NAM) and Rabinowitz's involvement in the organization. The series is divided into six subseries according to the functions, activities, projects, and interests of the organization. Additional materials concerning NAM can be found in the separate collection held by the Archives Service Center: New American Movement, Pittsburgh Chapter Records, 1973-1982, AIS.1989.18.
  Originally founded in Minneapolis, Minnesota, in 1971 as a result of the anti-war movement, NAM was established in an effort to build a "new left." Shortly after, regional chapters were established throughout the country. At its height, NAM had chapters in about 30 places (many of them being campuses) with about 5,000 members. It was supported by dues, fundraisers and donations. The organization stressed the importance of "political work and mass organizing as a means for transformation" and worked to "develop programs that would unify working people and catalyze a large mass movement for socialism." Classism, sexism, racism, imperialism, and capitalism were many of the issues the organization advocated against. The organization was also concerned with a host of international issues concerning Spain, Africa, Latin America, the Middle East, and China. As a founding member of the Pittsburgh chapter, part of the steering committee, and primary creator of the chapter newsletter, Rabinowitz was heavily involved and committed to the organization. She also attended all of the national conventions.
  In 1971, Rabinowitz helped found the Pittsburgh chapter. The chapter initially committed itself to anti-war activities -- organizing panel discussions, demonstrations, and pickets. In 1973 it helped fight for the impeachment of President Nixon. Due to the labor climate of the time, the organization eventually became heavily involved in workplace organizing, as well as social services and political education. Within the NAM were a number of commissions, such as the Energy Commission, that in 1975 devoted a considerable amount of time to speaking against the energy industry and its impending rate hikes, which included Duquesne Light. The Pennsylvania Alliance for Jobs and Energy (PAJE) is a result of this, an organization Rabinowitz helped start.
  - Internal Business, 1972-1982; 1.
    This subseries, organized alphabetically, documents the organizational structure of NAM and its role within the scope of the national organization. Included are the chapter structure and by-laws, chapter history, internal reports, member lists, correspondence, records of the national interim committee, and instructions for chapter leaders. It also documents the organization's eventual merger in 1983 with the Democratic Socialists of America. The New American Movement, Pittsburgh Chapter Records, 1973-1982, AIS.1989.18, contain additional materials relating to internal business.
    - Chapter Evaluations, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chapter Structure and By-Laws, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Contacts, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Instructions on Leadership, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Internal Reports, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Names and Addresses for Local and National Chapters and Members, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - National and Regional Chapter Reports, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - National Interim Committee Candidacy Statements, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - National Interim Committee Endorsements, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - National Interim Committee Resolutions, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Newsletter Plans which Include Personal Notes, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Phone Tree, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Pittsburgh Chapter History, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Proposal for New Orientation Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Recruitment Guidelines, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Response Against Socialist Worker's Party Endorsements, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Speakers Bureau and Fundraising Brochures, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Staff Job Descriptions, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Steering Committee Notes, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Strategy Papers, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - What is the NAM, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Various Materials, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Publications, 1973-1981; 2.
    This subseries contains the various publications that NAM produced, especially those of the local chapter. Organized alphabetically, the publications include general mailings sent to members of the local chapter which reported on the various happenings of the organization; the chapter newsletter, which Rabinowitz was instrumental in the creation and distribution of; and various leaflets announcing chapter meetings and events. The collection originally included a substantial amount of national NAM materials like instructional guides for organizing and running chapters, the national newsletter Moving On, and national discussion bulletins, but these materials were eliminated due to being already included in the "New American Movement, Pittsburgh Chapter Records" collection.
    - Chapter General Mailings, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Chapter General Mailings, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Chapter Mailings, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Chapter Mailings, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Chapter Newsletter, October 1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Chapter Newsletter, January-November 1973 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Chapter Newsletter, March and Jul-Oct 1974 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Chapter Newsletter, January-December 1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Chapter Newsletter, Feb-Sep 1976 and December 1976 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Chapter Newsletter, February-December 1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Chapter Newsletter, January-December 1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Chapter Newsletter, January 1979-January 1980 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Chapter Newsletter, February-December 1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Chapter Newsletter, January-December 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Chapter Newsletter, January-December 1982 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Literature, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Leaflets, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Papers by Frank Ackerman, Leon Blum, Harry C. Boyte, Logan Martinez, and Ed Meek, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Events, 1973-1985; 3.
    This subseries documents the various events the Pittsburgh chapter of NAM conducted or was involved in. Folders are organized alphabetically and include materials that document the local and national conferences and conventions, most of which Rabinowitz attended, as well as the film and dinner series, concerts and various other events held for or by the organization.
    - Conferences, Conventions, and Events, 1975-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Events, 1976-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Film and Dinner Series, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Films, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Fundraising Party Invitation, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "A Morality Play" for the Pittsburgh Counter-Inaugural Ball, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - National Council Conference, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - National NAM Utilities Conference, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Robin Tyler Concerts Planning, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Solidarity Day and Aftermath, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Vietnam Peace Treaty Celebration, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Projects, 1976-1982; 4.
    This subseries contains materials that document the various NAM projects that Rabinowitz was involved in. Folders are organized alphabetically. The People's History Project and The People's Power Project make up a large portion of this subseries. The People's History Project was created in order to bring awareness to the region's labor history which resulted in the creation of a slideshow and people's history calendar. The People's Power Project was created in reaction to the energy crisis and acted as a form of outreach in order to bring awareness to the issue and inspire greater public involvement. In 1976 the People's Power Project testified at hearings for a Lifeline bill in order to push for energy rate restructuring. Rabinowitz, an experienced fundraiser, was responsible for the creation of the advertising book included in this subseries.
    - Advertising Book, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Energy Commission Newsletter, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Feminism in Chapters, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Lifeline, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Lifeline Membership Lists, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - National Materials from NAM Utilities Project, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Pennsylvania Utility Commission Hearings, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - People's History Calendar Planning, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - People's History Project Correspondence Concerning the "1905 A People's History" Slideshow, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - People's History Slideshow Proposal, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - People's Power Project, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - People's Power Project Newsletters, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - People's Power Project Notes and Minutes, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - People's Power Project Slideshow Scripts, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - People's Power Project Media Coverage, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Political Education Committee, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Socialist School, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Workplace Organizing Taskforce, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Issues, 1973-1983; 5.
    Organized alphabetically, this subseries documents the local, national, and international issues NAM was involved or interested in. Often times, these subject files were utilized for NAM projects and literature. Topics include abortion, anti-Nixon, gay rights, and women's issues, just to name a few. This is not a complete reflection of the organization's interests and involvement, but rather represents the issues that Rabinowitz kept materials on.
    - Abortion, 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Anti-Nixon, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Attica, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Cuba, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Gay Rights, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - JP Stevens Boycott, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Local and National Nuclear Issues, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - National Health Security in Pittsburgh, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Puerto Rican Solidarity, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Reproductive Rights, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - University of Pittsburgh Faculty Organizing, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Vietnam, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Women, 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Related Organizations, 1971-1985; 6.
    NAM helped found and was involved in a number of local organizations. While these organizations fell under the auspices of NAM or were led by NAM members, they did not claim NAM affiliation since people during the time were often reluctant to join socialist organizations. The Pennsylvania Alliance for Jobs and Energy, the Public Power Movement, and the Coalition for Human Needs are examples of this. This subseries includes organizational records and is organized alphabetically.
    - Anti-Vietnam, National Organizations, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Big Red Food Club Collective, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Coalition for Human Needs, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Coalition for Human Needs City Budget Campaign, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Coalition for Human Needs City Budget Campaign Press Coverage, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - National Committee Against Repressive Legislation and the Criminal Reform Act of 1975 (S1), 1975-1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - New Jewish Agenda, 1972-1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Pennsylvania Alliance for Jobs and Energy (PAJE), 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Pennsylvania Alliance for Jobs and Energy (PAJE), 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - PAJE Newsletter, 1982-1983,1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - PAJE Advertising Handbook, Fundraising and Planning, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Pittsburgh Against Apartheid, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Pittsburgh Neighborhood Alliance, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Public Power Movement, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - South Africa and Pittsburgh, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)